Will you bump fists with me?
（ナルト）拳を合わせてくれっか？
（ミナト）ああ。
Yeah.
（ミナト）ああ　やってみよう。
Yeah, let's try it!
九尾　いや　九喇嘛の力を借りれば
できないことはない。
There's nothing we can't do
if we borrow Nine Tails'...
I mean, Kurama's power.
All right!
よし！　じゃ　４人で
力を合わせてやんぜ！
Then let's all four of us join forces!
（九喇嘛）４人か
わしらを人扱いするとは→
All four of us, eh?
You treat us like we're human too.
What kind of childrearing
has led to this, eh?
どう育ったら　そうなった？　フフフ。
ナルト。
ん？
Naruto...
Huh?
（ミナト）今のお前と　もっとゆっくり
いろいろ話して…。
I wish there was more time
to talk to the grown-up you!
Guys don't need to talk!
男は　いちいち言わなくていい。
もう　わかってっから！
I already know!
もう　母ちゃんの
チャクラとは会ったんだ。
I...already met Mom's chakra...
言いてぇことは
口うるせぇ母ちゃんと同じだろ！
What you want to say is the same
as my nagging mom, right?!
もう　わかってっからな！
I already know!
《この感じ　懐かしい感覚だ。
This feeling is so familiar...
これほど追いつめられているのに
何でもやれそうな　そんな…。
Even though we're out of options,
it feels like we can
accomplish anything...
そうだ　まるで
クシナといるときみたいな→
That's right! It's just like
when I was with Kushina!
そんな感覚》
力が　わいてきたってばよ！
このままいくぞ！
I feel power welling up inside me!
Let's go!
《サスケ：ナルトは
これほどのチャクラを！》
Naruto's got this much chakra?
（扉間）ナルト　威勢のよい声を上げ
かっこつけるのはよい。
Naruto! Letting out a shout
and showing off
is all well and good...
だが　まさかとは思うが→
but don't tell me
you've already forgotten...
仙術以外は効かぬということ
忘れてはおらぬだろうな？
that nothing other than
Sage Jutsu works against him?
お前も　バカではない！
I know you're not an idiot!
That's right!
そうでした～！
よし　お前は兄者以上のバカだ！
You're a bigger idiot
than my elder brother!
《これほどのチャクラも
持ち腐れとはな》
All that chakra and
it's being wasted on him...
《そんな感覚…　でもないか》
Or perhaps this isn't quite
the same feeling...
ガハハハ！
もう先代の　どの火影をも
超えてるぜ　そういう意味じゃな。
It looks like you've surpassed
all the previous Hokage, in stupidity!
うるせぇぞ　九喇嘛のバーカ！　バーカ！
Shut up! Stupid, stupid Kurama!
ハハハ！　バカは親近感も抱かれやすい。
Fools are easily liked
and trusted by others.
だが　気にするな。
そこは心配いらん。
It'll be all right.
Don't worry about it.
べ…　別に　バカなのは
心配してねえよ　俺ってば。
I-I'm not worried that I'm an idiot!
いや　そこじゃねえ。
えっ？
I'm not talking about that.
Huh?
その状態のまま
仙人化できるかもしれねえ。
I'm saying that you might
be able to go into Sage Mode
そういう意味で言ったんだ。
while you're in that state.
いいか　お前は
忘れているかもしれねえが→
Listen up... You've probably
already forgotten,
ペイン長門ってのと
最後　やり合ったときだ。
but during your final battle
with Pain, Nagato...
ヤツの言い分に　わしも
怒りがおさえられなくなってな。
I got so mad by what he was saying
that my chakra leaked out,
あのとき　お前は
ちょうど仙人の状態だったが→
even though you were
in Sage Mode at that time.
わしのチャクラが出すぎて→
My power and your Sage Power
actually managed to synchronize.
わしの力と仙人の力が
うまく同調したことがあった。
う～ん…。
そんなこと　あったっけ？
Did something like that
happen back then...?
あ～っ！！
そういうお前は
仙人修業のときに→
You say that, but back when
I was undergoing Sage Training,
じいちゃん仙人との仙人の術
邪魔しただろうが！
you interfered with Gramps Sage's
Sage Jutsu, remember?
わしは　カエルなんぞと
ルームシェアする気はなかったからだ！
That's because I had no interest
in sharing the same space with toads!
それにな　わしのチャクラがありながら
お前は仙術に頼った。
Besides, it really pissed me off
that you would rely on Sage Jutsu
それも気にくわねえ！
when you had my chakra.
この意地っ張り野郎。
You stubborn bastard!
だから　そりゃ　テメエだろ！！
You're the stubborn one!
つまり　言いてぇのは
今なら　わしの力を使いつつ→
Anyway, what I'm trying to say is,
that I'm willing to let you use
仙人の力も許してやるってことだ。
both my power and
Sage Power right now.
それの　どこが
意地っ張りだ　この野郎！
What's stubborn about that,
damn it?!
素直じゃないんだから～。
You just can't be up front about
your feelings, can you?
テメエ！　最近　わしのこと
ナメてねえか？　こら！！
You bastard! You've been
making fun of me a lot lately!
いや　親近感ってやつだってばよ。
It's not like that...
It's out of familiarity...
チッ！
尾獣化と仙術を同時にやるか…。
Using Tailed Beast State with
Sage Jutsu at the same time, huh...
ガキと同じで　わしが入ってんだ。
You've got the same me
inside you as your son.
You should be able to provide him
with powerful support.
お前は強力なサポートができるはずだ。
ああ！
Yeah...
わかってるよ　そんなこと！
I already know that!
《術も準備しておくよ》
I'll have some jutsu prepared too!
《これだと
自然エネルギーの吸収が速ぇ》
I'm absorbing Nature Energy
a lot faster in this state.
よ～し！
All right!
The Divine Tree
ナルト！
螺旋丸に仙術を加えてくれ！
Naruto, add Sage Jutsu
to the Rasengan!
オッケー！
Okay!
Old Man Second!
二代目のおっちゃん！
Let's do it!
いくぞ！
Just forge ahead!
そのままいけ！　ヤツの攻撃は
わしたちのチャクラで受け流す。
We'll ward off his attacks
with our chakra!
– Rasengan!
（２人）螺旋丸！
（２人）おぉ～！
That black thing sure is solid!
硬ってぇな　あの黒いの。
クソッ　今度はガードされちまった。
Damn it...
He blocked us this time!
（扉間）やはり読まれていたな。
He predicted our attack...
飛雷神
一辺倒の作戦では苦しいな。
Using only the Flying Raijin
in our strategy isn't enough.
Our only option is to destroy
that black thing!
あの黒いの
ぶっ壊すしかねえってばよ！
どうする？
But how?
All right, next up...
よ～し！　なら次は→
Let's try adding Sage Jutsu
to a Tailed Beast Bomb!
この尾獣玉に
仙術を加えてやるってばよ！
よし　いいぞ！
All right, excellent idea!
《お前はもしかすると
兄者以上の火影に…》
You might just surpass
my Elder Brother as Hokage...
そっちの九喇嘛も協力してくれ。
Hey, other Kurama! You help too!
そうこなくっちゃね。
I like the sound of that!
I thought so...
《やっぱり…。
懐かしい感覚だ》
This is a familiar feeling,
after all!
《これが今のナルト…。
This is what Naruto is
capable of now?
これほどのチャクラを完璧に…》
He's able to control this much
chakra perfectly...
How far will you...
《お前は　どこまで…》
There's no harm
in taking measures early.
《オビト：早めに手を打つに
越したことはない》
なっ…。
なんだ？
W-What's that?!
（柱間）うおっ！
《マダラ：もう
無限月読を始める気か？》
He's starting
the Infinite Tsukuyomi already?!
He spit out the Ten Tails?
十尾を吐き出しやがったのか。
Be careful. I have
a bad feeling about this.
気をつけて　嫌な感じだ。
I'll suspend the barrier for now.
いったん結界を止めるか。
（いの）結界が消えていく！
The barrier is disappearing!
Now we can fight alongside Naruto
and the others!
（チョウジ）これで　ナルトたちと一緒に
戦えるね！
《こ…　これは…》
Th-This is—!
うわっ！
What?!
うわぁ～！
Run! It will absorb all your chakra
in one swoop!
逃げろ！　コイツ　チャクラを一気に
吸収しちまうぞ！
うわぁ～！
It's coming after us one by one!
一人ひとり確実に
生きてる俺たちを狙ってんだ！
But why...?!
Why...?! Why do I get so many
coming at me, huh?
（キラービー）なんで…。
なんで俺だけ
こんなに多いんだバカ野郎！
Fool... Ya fool!
この野郎！
This is the tree of God.
It's called the Divine Tree!
（牛鬼）これが神の木
その名も神樹だ。
It's the Ten Tails' final form!
十尾の最終形態だ。
お前のチャクラが　他のヤツらより多い
ってわかってやがったんだ。
It knows that you have
more chakra than everyone else!
At this rate, the chakra that Naruto gave
to everyone is meaningless.
これじゃ　ナルトが　みんなに渡した
チャクラも意味がねえ。
コイツはいったいなんぞ！？
W-What is this?!
本来チャクラとは　この神樹のものだ。
Chakra first originated with...
this Divine Tree!
All the chakra here...
ここにある　すべてのチャクラ
そして　お前の莫大なチャクラもな。
Even the enormous amounts
of chakra you possess.
What?
（柱間）なに？
Humans stole chakra from
the Divine Tree long ago.
（マダラ）かつて神樹から
チャクラを奪ったのは　人のほうだ。
It's just trying to take back
what belongs to it.
これは　それを
取り返そうとしてるだけだ。
何の話だ？
What are you talking about?!
果てしない時の流れは
本来の事柄に霧をかけていく。
The endless passing of time
has cast a fog over the truth.
なぜ　忍が生まれたか
知っているか　柱間。
Do you know how shinobi
came to be, Hashirama?
まだ　人がチャクラという
その概念すら持たぬ　はるか昔。
Long ago, when people didn't
even have a concept of chakra...
（マダラ）そのときでさえ
人は互いに争い続けていた。
...even then, people still battled
each other.
神樹は　そんな争いに
関わることなく→
The Divine Tree was never involved
in their battles
and was worshipped as
a sacred pillar.
ずっと　人々から神の柱
神柱として崇められてきた。
そして　ある日→
But one day...
１，０００年に一度実るという
神樹の実が宿った。
The Divine Tree bore a fruit
that was said to be produced
only once in a millennium.
I don't know what it signified,
but legend dictated
それに　どんな意味があったのかは
わからぬが→
決して　その実に
手をつけてはならぬ→
that no one was to ever
lay hands on the fruit.
というのが伝承だった。
しかし　そんな折→
But one princess, in her desire
争いに勝つため
神樹の力を得ようと→
to reap the power of
the Divine Tree to win a war,
その禁断の実に手をつけ
口にした姫がいた。
took and consumed the forbidden fruit.
神の力を得た姫は→
Afterwards, she gained
the power of a god,
and it was said she quashed
the war by herself.
人々の争いを
たった一人でおさめたという。
その姫の名は　大筒木かぐや。
Her name was Kaguya Otsutsuki.
では　それが…。
So that's how!
最初にチャクラを持った
人間だった。
She was the first human
to have chakra.
（マダラ）やがて
かぐやに子ができるが→
Eventually, Kaguya would bear a child
その赤子は　生まれながらに
チャクラをその身に宿していた。
who was born with chakra
already within him.
だが　チャクラを取られた神樹は→
However, the Divine Tree
came alive
and went on a rampage
in order to reclaim its stolen chakra.
それを取り返そうと
動き暴れ出した。
それが　十尾だ。
That is the Ten Tails.
そして　それを止めたのが
かぐやの子だった。
And the one who stopped it
was Kaguya's child.
His name was Hagoromo Otsutsuki.
名を　大筒木ハゴロモ。
チャクラの教えを説き
忍宗を始めた忍の祖。
He was the one who preached
the teachings of chakra,
and was the founder of Ninshu.
六道仙人と呼ばれた男だ。
He was the forefather of the shinobi—
the man known as
the Sage of Six Paths.
どうして　そんなことをお前が！？
How do you know all of this?!
うちはの石碑に
しるされていることだ。
It was inscribed on
the Uchiha Stone Tablet.
争いを止めるために
禁断の実に手をつけた人が→
Do I need to explain what happened
to those who tasted of
the forbidden fruit...
その後　どうなってしまったか
説明がいるか？
for the purpose of ending all conflict?
（マダラ）そう　何も変わらなかった。
That's right...
It didn't change anything.
それどころか
更に　争いは凄惨になったのだ。
In fact, subsequent wars
become more gruesome!
俺は　それを知って絶望した。
Upon learning this,
I fell into despair.
この世界に
本当の夢はないのだよ　柱間。
There are no such things as true dreams
in this world, Hashirama!
その実に人が
手をつけたときより→
Ever since people tasted that fruit,
humans have been cursed...
人は呪われ　より憎しみ合うことを
決定づけられたのだ。
And destined to hate
each other even more!
忍そのものが　その愚かさを
象徴する存在だとは思わないか。
And it is we shinobi
whose very existence
symbolizes that foolishness,
don't you think?
それならば　いっそ…。
In which case I'd rather...
またこの神樹に頼った力が
大幻術か。
So relying on the power
of the Divine Tree again
by using a great genjutsu...
((お前は　見えないのさ。
更にこの先が　先の夢が…))
You just can't see it...
What's beyond this...
The dreams of the far future.
お前の言っていた
更に先の夢だってのか？
Is this what you meant
by "dreams of the far future"?!
ああ。　だが　ほんの少し違う。
Yes...
But it will be a little different.
うわ～っ！
ナルト！
Naruto!
水遁　水断波！
Water Style: Severing Wave!
クソッ　多すぎる。
Damn it! There are too many of them!
《これでは
ナルトを感知できても意味がない》
I might be able to sense Naruto,
but it's useless!
四代目　ナルトのところへ
直接　飛べるか？
Fourth! Can you teleport directly
to Naruto?!
無理です！　さっきの飛雷神と
このツタにチャクラを奪われてしまった。
I can't! That last Flying Raijin
and these vines have drained my chakra!
（扉間）ならば。
In that case...
離しやがれ…。
Let go...of me...
《じいちゃん…》
Gramps...
遅くなってすまんのう。
Sorry it took so long!
Oh!
おお　猿！
Saru!
（扉間）よし　ここから飛ぶぞ。
All right!
We're teleporting out of here!
（重吾）やっと　落ち着いたか。
Have things finally settled down?
く…　くっ！
（柱間）お前の言っていた
更に先の夢だってのか！？
Is this what you meant by
"dreams of the far future"?!
（マダラ）ああ…
だが　ほんの少し違う。
Yes...
But it will be a little different.
違うだと！？
"A little different"?
見ろ。
Take a look...
（マダラ）この神樹のつぼみが
開花したとき→
When the Divine Tree's bud
finally blooms...
花の中の眼が天上の月に写り→
The moon will reflect the eye
at the flower's center, up above...
無限月読は完全となる。
and the Infinite Tsukuyomi
will be fully activated...
そして　それを為すのは　この俺だ。
And I...will be the one
to accomplish it.
もうダメだ…。
こんなことって…。
We're doomed!
This is crazy...
（カツユ）サクラさん！
サクラさん　大丈夫ですか？
Miss Sakura!
Are you all right, Miss Sakura?
くっ…　ハァハァ…　やばかったっての。
バカ野郎　この野郎。
That was a close call, fool! Ya fool!
（いの）うっ…　危なかった。
ハァ　ハァ…。
That was too close!
Is it over?
おさまったのかな？
あぁ！？
（オビト）もう…　じっとしていろ。
Now, be still...
お前らは…　十分　耐え忍んだ。
You have all...
endured plenty already.
Shinobi are done for.
＜　きょうから１４代目＞
＜旬の小鉢が
大好きな豆助＞
♪～
豆助　きょうは今が旬の
アレを使った小鉢よ？
＜　その小鉢とは…＞